Guide to the Parliamentary Speeches, Debates, Etc.
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
[Parliamentary speeches, debates, etc., and other miscellaneous manuscripts]
1620-1629
OSBORN FB138
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.13
(1 volume)
Collection of 46 manuscripts, in multiple secretary hands, of Parliamentary speeches and miscellaneous notes. Many of the Parliamentary speeches concern the power and influence of George Villiers, Duke of Buckingham, including a remonstrance by the House of Commons against the Duke of Buckingham's influence on Charles I; John Digby, Earl of Bristol's response to charges of high treason for his opposition to the Duke of Buckingham; and a speech by Richard Weston, Earl of Portland, conveying King Charles I's displeasure with speeches against the Duke. Other speeches include several complaining about the influence of Catholicism; a speech by Sir Edward Coke on the Petition of Right; and speeches by Charles I and James I to Parliament.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
For provenance information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The following finding aid is a complete inventory of the contents of Osborn fb138. This list was reformatted from previously existing cataloging.
Chess -- Great Britain; Metals -- Handbooks, manuals, etc.; Nobility -- England; Religious poetry, English; Great Britain -- History; Great Britain -- Politics and government -- 1603-1649; Great Britain -- Religious life and customs -- 17th century; Charles, King of England, I, 1600-1649; James, King of England, I, 1566-1625; Bristol, John Digby, Earl of, 1580-1654; Buckingham, George Villiers, Duke of, 1592-1628; Coke, Edward, Sir, 1552-1634; Portland, Richard Weston, Earl of, 1577-1635; Great Britain. Parliament
- OSBORN fb138
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1629. HOUSE OF COMMONS.
    - [Seven speeches concerning grievances on religion, ca. 1629.], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      9 p.; 30 x 19 cm.
      Contemporary MS copies.
      Speeches by: Edward Kirton (f.1621-
      43); Francis Rous (1579-1659); Sir
      Robert Phelips (1586?-1636); Sir
      Walter Erle (1586?-1655); Sir John
      Eliot (1592-1632); Sir Francis
      Seymour, 1st Baron Seymour of
      Trowbridge (1590?-1664) and John Pym
      (1584-1643). Compare with Wallace
      Notestein's "Commons Debates 1629"
      for variations in texts and dates.
      folder 1.
  - COKE, SIR EDWARD, 1552-1634
    - [Speech concerning the Petition of Right made at a conference of the two houses, 1628 Apr 9, reported by the Bishop of Lincoln, ca. 1628.], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      7 p.; 30 x 19 cm.
      Contemporary MS copy.
      Printed in Rushworth, "Historical
      Collections" vol. I, p. 532-537.
      Great Britain. Parliament, 1628
      Great Britain. Constitutional Law
      William, John, Archbishop of York,
      1582-1650.
      folder 2.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1628. HOUSE OF COMMONS.
    - [Remonstrance of Commons against the Duke of Buckingham, June, 1628.], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      10 p.; 31 x 20 cm.
      Complaint of Commons against
      influence of George Villiers, 1st
      Duke of Buckingham (1592-1628) in
      Charles I's governmental decisions.
      Printed in Rushworth I, 619-626.
      Accompanied by calendar of shipping
      lost to the enemy in the previous
      three years.
      folder 3.
  - JAMES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1566-1625
    - "His majesty's speache at the Parliament begun the 4th of February Anno 1621", [ca. 1621] (Box 1)
      6 p.; 31 x 21 cm.
      The parliamentary session was
      actually opened by James I on 30
      January 1621.
      Great Britain. Parliament, 1621.
      House of Commons.
      folder 4.
  - BRISTOL, JOHN DIGBY, 1ST EARL OF, 1580-1653
    - "The Earl of Bristolls speache in Parliament, 6 May 1626", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      17 p.; 31 x 20 cm.
      Speech in response to charges of high
      treason because of opposition to
      George Villiers, 1st Duke of
      Buckingham (1592-1628). Mostly
      printed in Rushworth I, 254-261.
      Great Britain. Parliament, 1626.
      House of Lords.
      folder 5.
  - BUCKINGHAM, GEORGE VILLIERS, 1ST DUKE OF, 1592-1628
    - "An explanation from the kinge delivered by the Duke of Buckingham at a committee of both houses in the painted chamber, 30 March 1626", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      20 p.; 31 x 20 cm.
      Accompanied by discussions of Edward
      Conway, 1st Viscount Conway (d.1631)
      and Buckingham, mostly printed, with
      variations, in Rushworth I, 225-235.
      folder 6.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1626. HOUSE OF COMMONS.
    - [The remonstrance of Commons in Parliament, 5 April 1626.], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      4 p.; 31 x 20 cm.
      "To the king's most Excellent
      Majesty, the humble remonstrance of
      the commons now assembled in
      Parliament."
      Printed in Rushworth I, 243.
      Charles I., 1600-49.
      folder 7.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-49
    - "The Kings Majesties Speech 6 February 1625", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      Given at the opening of the 1626
      session.
      folder 8.
  - COVENTRY, THOMAS COVENTRY, 1ST BARON, 1578-1640
    - "The Lord Keepers speech [on the king's behalf] 6 February 1626", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      3 p.; 30 x 21 cm.
      Printed in Rushworth I, 202-203,
      with variations at the end.
  - FINCH, SIR HENEAGE, D. 1631
    - "Speech at the Parliament House, 8 February 1625", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      1 p.; 31 x 20 cm.
      Contemporary MS copy, accompanied by
      reply of Lord Keeper (Thomas
      Coventry, 1st Baron Coventry [1578-
      1640]), and Finch's speech about the
      nature and goals of Commons (in
      Rushworth I, 204-207), and another
      reply by the Lord Keeper.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1626. HOUSE OF COMMONS.
    - [Reply to Weston's message from the King] 13 March 1625, [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      Portland, Richard Weston, 1st Earl
      of, 1577-1635.
  - PEMBROKE, WILLIAM HERBERT, 3RD EARL OF, 1580-1630
    - "The Lord Chamberlain's speech on 7 March 1625", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      "Gentlemen I am commanded by the
      House of Peers..."
  - TURNER, SAMUEL, D. 1647?
    - "Doctor Turner's Queries in Parliament, 11 March 1625", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      2 p.; 31 x 20 cm.
      Accompanied by Turner's explanation
      to the queries about the power of
      Buckingham (1582-1628).
      Printed in Rushworth I, 217.
  - PORTLAND, RICHARD WESTON, 1ST EARL OF, 1577-1635
    - "The Chancellor's Message, 14 March 1625", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      "The King is displeased with the
      speeches of Mr. Cooke and Dr. Turner
      against the Duke of Buckingham."
      House of Commons; Turner, Samuel, d.
      1647?; Cook, Sir John, d. 1644
      Buckingham, George Villiers, 1st Duke
      of, 1592-1628.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1626. HOUSE OF COMMONS.
    - "The answer of the Commons to the message of the King, touching supply and grievances, 15 March 1625", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      Followed by the King's answer, 15
      March 1625. Charles I, 1600-49.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-49
    - "King Charles his speech the first day of his going to the Parliament, [6] February 1625", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      the Lord Keeper's speech on Charles's
      behalf, printed in Rushworth I,
      202-203.
      House of Commons; Coventry, Thomas
      Coventry, 1st baron, 1578-1640.
      folder 9.
  - TURNER, SAMUEL, D. 1647?
    - "Doctor Turner's 6 Queries in Parliament, 11 March 1626", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      On the Duke of Buckingham.
  - PORTLAND, RICHARD WESTON, 1ST EARL OF, 1577-1635
    - "His majesty's speech delivered by messenger to the Commons in the lower house of Parliament by Sir Richard Weston, 13 March 1625", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      Stresses the need for supply.
      Printed in Rushworth I, 215.
      Charles I, 1600-49; Great Britain.
      Parliament, 1626. House of Commons.
  - WALTER, SIR WILLIAM
    - "Sir William Walter's speech in Parliament, 20 March 1625", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      Printed in Rushworth I, 218.
  - TURNER, SAMUEL, D. 1647?
    - "An explanation of Turner's queries, March 1626", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
  - ELIOT, SIR JOHN, 1592-1632
    - "Sir John Eliot in the Parliament his speech, 27 March 1626", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      Printed in Rushworth I, 220.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-49
    - "The King's speech in the hall at Whitehall, 29 March 1626", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      Accompanied by Lord Keeper's speech
      to both houses at Whitehall, and the
      King's further speech. All printed
      in Rushworth I, 221-225, with
      variations. Great Britain.
      Parliament, 1626; Coventry, Thomas
  - BUCKINGHAM, GEORGE VILLIERS, 1ST DUKE OF, 1592-1628
    - "An explanation from the king delivered by the Duke of Buckingham, 30 March 1626", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      5 p.; 31 x 20 cm.
      With speeches by Edward Conway, 1st
      Viscount Conway (d. 1631); the Lord
      Chamberlain, William Herbert, 3rd
      Earl of Pembroke (1580-1630); and
      Buckingham. Charles I, 1600-49
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1626. HOUSE OF COMMONS.
    - "The Remonstrance of the Commons now assembled in Parliament, 1 April 1626", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      Addressed to "the King's most
      excellent majesty."
      Charles I, 1600-49.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-49
    - "The King's letter to the Earl of Bristol, dated 20 January 1625/6", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      "We have received your letter
      addressed to us by Buckingham..."
      Bristol, John Digby, 1st earl of,
      1580-1654.
  - BRISTOL, JOHN DIGBY, 1ST EARL OF, 1580-1654
    - "The Humble petition of the Earl of Bristol to the House of Lords, April 1626", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      1 p. 31 x 20 cm.
      Accompanied by the Lord Keeper's
      message from the King regarding
      Bristol's petition, which is printed
      in Rushworth I, 237.
      House of Lords; Coventry, Thomas
      Coventry, 1st Baron, 1578-1640
  - WILLIAM, JOHN, ARCHBISHOP OF YORK, 1582-1650
    - "The Bishop of Lincoln's letter to Charles I", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      "Most mighty and dread sovereign, I
      have now these few months..."
  - BRISTOL, JOHN DIGBY, 1ST EARL OF, 1580-1654
    - "Articles of the Earl of Bristol against the Duke of Buckingham, 1 May 1626", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      Printed in Rushworth I, 262-263.
  - BRISTOL, JOHN DIGBY, 1ST EARL OF, 1580-1654
    - "Articles of the Earl of Bristol against the Lord Conway put into the House of Parliament, 1 May 1626", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      Printed in Rushworth I, 264-265.
      Great Britain. Parliament, 1626
      Conway, Edward Conway, 1st viscount,
      d. 1631.
  - DIGGES, SIR DUDLEY, 1583-1639
    - "The Commons Declaration and Accusation of the Duke of Buckingham, May 1626", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      Presented by Sir Dudley Digges.
      See Rushworth I, 306-341.
      House of Commons; Buckingham, George
      Villiers, 1st duke of, 1592-1628.
  - COOK, SIR JOHN, D. 1644
    - "Part of Sir John Cooke's speech or report in the Parliament House, 23 March 1625/6", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      Concerns assignments of English
      troops and disbursement of payments.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. TREATIES. 1625-49 (CHARLES I).
    - "The Treaty of the contract made between the King of England and the Hollanders, 1625 Sep 27", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      Great Britain -- foreign relations --
      Netherlands.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1626. HOUSE OF COMMONS.
    - "A copie of the Declaration of the House of Commons to the Lords, 11 May 1626", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      About the Duke of Buckingham.
      Printed in Rushworth I, 356-357.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-49
    - "The King's speech answering the commons speech made the day before, 11 May 1626", [ca. 1626] (Box 1)
      "The cause of my coming this day..."
      House of Commons. folder 9.
  - [ANONYMOUS]
    - [Notes on the game of chess, ca. 1620.], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      7 p.; 31 x 20 cm.
      Anonymous manuscript.
      "The principle is to knowe the
      pieces to wite..."
      folder 10.
  - [ANONYMOUS]
    - "A booke intituled the fantasie of Idolatrie", [early 17th c] (Box 1)
      2 p; 31 x 20 cm.
      Anonymous MS poem.
      25 stanzas, beginning "All Christian
      People." With note at end, "Thus
      ended this little treatise made and
      compiled by Gray. In the Marters
      Book." Idols and images -- worship
      English poetry.
      folder 11.
  - [ANONYMOUS]
    - [Metallurgy -- tables, calculations, etc.], n.d. (Box 1)
      12 p.; 31 x 20 cm.
      Notes on the assaying, refining, and
      use of gold and silver. How to
      convert Flemish weights into English
      equivalents; how to determine amount
      of gold in silver; melting of gold
      how to prepare silver for dipping in
      sulphuric acid, etc.
      folder 12.
  - [ANONYMOUS]
    - "Vox populi or Newes from Spaine, according to the Spanish copie translated", [ca. 1620] (Box 1)
      16 p.; 31 x 20 cm.
      Report on a council called by Philip
      III, King of Spain (1578-1621), for
      the Spanish states to hear the report
      of the Spanish Ambassador to England,
      presided over by Francisco de
      Sandoval y Rojas, Duke of Lerma
      (1552-1625). Printed by Thomas Scott
      under the same title in 1620.
      James I, 1566-1625.
      folder 13.
  - [ANONYMOUS]
    - [Notes on the creation of peers, from Richard II to Elizabeth I], [ca. 1620] (Box 1)
      6 p.; 31 x 20 cm.
      Great Britain -- nobility.
      folder 14.
  - [ANONYMOUS]
    - [Notes on the history of England], [ca. 1620] (Box 1)
      Includes biographical accounts of
      rulers from William the Conqueror to
      Elizabeth I.
      Great Britain -- kings and rulers.
      folder 15.